[SPEAKER_00]: How can I solve all my problems?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's a good question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, all the problems can be solved if you see that all problems are caused by craving for which you are responsible.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no problem if there's no suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, when there is a problem, it means something is a problem because it's making you suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm sick, I get...
[SPEAKER_00]: I've got a headache.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, headache in itself, it's not a problem, nor is it a suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: You not wanting it to be that way, and not wanting to have a headache, while having or not having headache, is not in your control.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you crave to get rid of the circumstances that you find displeasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, you create a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: At the root of every suffering, it's craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible to experience suffering without having the present craving present in your experience as your attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha said that the root of suffering is craving, not the external circumstances, however bad they might be.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, being in poverty...
[SPEAKER_01]: Poverty is not suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Poverty is hardship.
[SPEAKER_01]: But hardship does not need to be suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, again, on a fundamental level, if you want to describe the nature of craving, there's three types.
[SPEAKER_01]: When circumstances are pleasing, you're craving for more of that pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: If circumstances are displeasing,
[SPEAKER_01]: You're craving for that... this pleasure to disappear, to not be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to get rid of it instantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the third type is the subtlest to see, but basically the circumstances are neither good nor bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: You kind of crave towards indolence and searching excitement or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: But people... people... people fear boredom.
[SPEAKER_01]: They fear the...
[SPEAKER_01]: Like a neutral environment, which is neither good nor bad, they can't recognize it as peaceful.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that... in that very manner, a person is fully responsible for all of the suffering that he experiences in his life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there was... there were even cases in the suttas that the Buddha was giving the example of, was the... even if a highway robbers attack you and sever your limb by limb and torture you, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: That, basically, won't be the suffering for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be your craving in regard to it, your hatred towards them, trying to get rid of it, thinking why are they doing this, they shouldn't be doing this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, trying to control the circumstances that are disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without recognizing that actually, fundamentally, they're not in your control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, you're responsible for lack of that knowledge, which then generates more craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just keep revolving around it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's also instead of trying to solve every little issue that you have.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when people don't see the... well, they don't see the root of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they think the suffering is the circumstances around them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then they try to address every single instance, every example, every issue, every person to talk to, everything disagreeable put away.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, that's usually what people's lives revolve around.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's endless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's endless because it's misapplied.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not applied where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is craving, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're basically trying to solve your suffering by... at a completely wrong place, where the suffering isn't.